Finding Aid for Diana Warshay Papers 1971-1979
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Diana Warshay Papers 1971-1979
Warshay, Diana.
2 linear feet
Michigan sociologist specializing in areas of abortion rights and crisis intervention training. She conducted study of Abortion referral agencies 1971-1973, one of whose members was the Michigan Clergy Counseling Service. She was also coordinator of the Detroit Police Department's Social Conflict Research Project, 1978-1979, and was one of the founders of the Tri-County Coalition Against Domestic Violence; correspondence, minutes, bylaws, newsletters, grant applications, and other materials relating to her work in studying abortion and domestic abuse cases.
0063 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Diana Warshay in October 1999 (donor no. 8889 ).
The collection is open for research.
Diana Warshay was a sociologist who worked in the areas of abortion rights and crisis intervention training. She taught at the University of Toledo in the Sociology Department.
The Michigan Clergy Counseling Service (MCCS) was a state-wide clergy abortion referral network which operated before abortion was made legal. Diana Warshay conducted studies of the circumstances of MCCS clients. The paper, "The Abortion Brokers: A Transactional Analysis of Organizational Development," included in this collection, is about MCCS.
Dr. Warshay coordinated the Detroit Police Department's Social Conflict Research Project (SCRP) in 1978 and 1979. The Social Conflict Task Force was formed in September 1977 and was responsible for directing overall SCRP activity. The objectives of the SCRP were to "provide crisis intervention training to a limited number of patrol and investigation officers assigned to a single police precinct" and to "provide a mechanism which will facilitate the process of criminal complaint filing for the female victim of domestic assaults" (from grant application). A third objective, added later, was to "increase the willingness of domestic assault victims to obtain the appropriate assistance or to pursue the appropriate action against their attacker(s), be that in the form of initiating civil or criminal proceedings or the seeking of medical treatment or professional counselling" (from subgrant adjustment request). These objectives were realized through a study of other police departments' crisis intervention programs, a search for a test precinct for training, victim surveys and police surveys before and after police training, and a training program for 250 officers.
Diana Warshay was one of the founders of the Tri-County Coalition Against Domestic Violence (TCCADV), which originated out of the SCRP and the Michigan Coalition Against Domestic Violence in April 1978. The primary purposes were to "collect and disseminate information on services for victims of domestic violence; collect information on, and educate the Tri-County community about the nature, extent, and effects of domestic violence; appraise services rendered to victims of domestic violence by community agencies and make recommendations for improvement and expansion of services; [and] provide a mechanism for the sharing and solicitation of resources in the area of domestic violence" (from bylaws). Dr. Warshay served on the board of directors.
The Diana Warshay Papers contain correspondence, minutes, bylaws, newsletters, grant applications, questionnaires, and FORTRAN coding forms and printouts. The collection documents Dr. Warshay's work in studying abortion and domestic abuse cases through the Michigan Clergy Counseling Service, the Tri-County Coalition Against Domestic Violence, and the Detroit Police Department's Social Conflict Research Project. Perhaps the most interesting elements of the collection are the Data Sheets for the Michigan Clergy Counseling Service which describe the circumstances surrounding women who sought abortions in the early 1970's and the Victim Study Telephone Surveys for the Social Conflict Research Project which describe the circumstances surrounding domestic abuse calls to the Detroit Police Department.
The papers are divided into three series: Michigan Clergy Counseling Service, Tri-County Coalition Against Domestic Violence, and Social Conflict Research Project.
Subjects:
Abortion--Michigan.; Crisis intervention mental health services.; Detroit (Mich.). Police Dept. Social Conflict Task Force.; Family violence--Michigan.; Michigan Clergy Counseling Service.; Tri-County Coalition Against Violence.; Warshay, Diana.
- Michigan Clergy Counseling Service (MCCS)
  The Michigan Clergy Counseling Service series (.3 linear ft., 1971-1973) is divided into five subseries: Correspondence, Annual Meeting Minutes, Paper, Clergy Questionnaire, and Abortion Study. The correspondence discusses surveying clergy, making arrangements for presenting the paper on the MCCS to sociological societies, and also includes general MCCS correspondence. The annual minutes describe the 1971/1972 activities of MCCS. The paper, "The Abortion Brokers: A Transactional Analysis of Organizational Development" evaluates MCCS from a sociological perspective. The blank clergy questionnaire evaluates the effectiveness of the organization. The abortion study contains a proposal that may correspond to the data sheets filled out by MCCS counselors which document abortion referrals. The FORTRAN coding key, forms, and printout standardize and quantify the surveys.
  - Correspondence October 1971-February 1973 (Box 1)
  - Annual Meeting Minutes May 17, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Paper, "The Abortion Brokers: A Transactional Analysis of Organizational Development," May 1972 (Box 1)
  - Clergy Questionnaire July 1972 (Box 1)
  - Abortion Study
    - Proposal (Box 1)
    - Data Sheets 1971-1973, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - FORTRAN Coding Key (Box 1)
    - FORTRAN Coding Forms, 1-2052 (gaps) (Box 1)
    - FORTRAN Coding Forms and Printout, 2100-5463 (gaps) (Box 1)
- Tri-County Coalition Against Domestic Violence (TCCADV)
  The Tri-County Coalition Against Domestic Violence series (.1 linear ft, 1978-1979) contains five subseries: Bylaws, Board of Directors Orientation Packet, Meeting Agendas and Minutes, Newsletters, and Funding Proposal. The Bylaws and Board of Directors Orientation Packet describe the purpose of the Coalition. The Meeting Agendas, Minutes, and Newsletters document the activities the TCCADV was involved in. Dr. Warshay worked on the Funding Proposal, which also describes the history and purpose of the TCCADV.
  - Bylaws July 1979 (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors Orientation Packet, Circa 1979 (Box 1)
  - Meeting Agendas and Minutes
    - TCCADV June 1978-September 1979 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Coalition Against Domestic Violence February 1979-November 1979 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters January 1979-November 1979 (Box 1)
  - Funding Proposal 1979 (Box 1)
- Social Conflict Research Project (SCRP)
  The Social Conflict Research Project series (1.6 linear ft., 1977-1979) contains six subseries: Background Information, Other Detroit Family Crisis Projects, Grant and Subgrants, Social Conflict Task Force, Crisis Intervention Training Course, and Victim Study. The Background Information subseries contains some documents which put into context the purpose of the SCRP and Warshay's involvement in it. The Other Detroit Family Crisis Projects subseries contains information on the Dearborn, and Detroit and Wayne County projects. The Grant and Subgrants subseries is the best source of information on the SCRP. It contains applications which describe the proposed project, and progress reports for the first year of the project. The Social Conflict Task Force subseries contains Duties of the Task Force, a Member Directory, Memos, Meeting Agendas, Minutes, and Reports. The Crisis Intervention Training Course subseries contains a Police Officer Survey which was used to design the course, an Outline of the course, and Critiques. The Victim Study was a telephone survey of domestic abuse 911 calls to the police which was planned to be conducted both before and after the training course in order to measure its effectiveness. The subseries contains Questionnaire Instructions and Coding Ranges, FORTRAN printouts of each record (one set believed to be Survey II because the sample number matches, and another labeled Survey III), and Telephone Surveys of each 911 caller. This collection retains 108 of the 220 answer sheets for Survey I, and all 108 of the answer sheets for Survey II.
  - Background Information (Box 1)
  - Other Detroit Family Crisis Projects 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - Grant and Subgrants
    - Applications February 1978-June 1978 (Box 1)
    - Quarterly Progress Reports 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - Social Conflict Task Force
    - Duties and Member Directory (Box 1)
    - Memos May 1978-February 1979 (Box 1)
    - Meeting Agendas, Minutes, and Reports October 1978-February 1979 (Box 1)
  - Crisis Intervention Training Course
    - Police Officer Survey and Coding Key (Box 1)
    - Outline (Box 1)
    - Critiques (Box 1)
  - Victim Study
    - Questionnaire Instructions and Coding Ranges (Box 1)
    - Printout of Each Record, Survey II? (1-108), Survey III (1-126) (Box 1)
    - Telephone Surveys
      - Survey I, 1-60, 5 folders (Box 1)
      - Survey I, 61-108, 4 folders (Box 2)
      - Survey II, 1-108, 11 folders (Box 2)